Magnesium. It's magnesium. I think
you'll be surprised by how nuanced this
topic is, though. Because while many
people talk about magnesium as if it's a
nutrient that we can't get enough of, I
have a far more cautious tale to tell,
and I'll prove it. Magnesium isn't all
good news. And when it comes to our
brain, there's a lot to say. So, let's
get into it. So yeah, many many millions
of people are low on their magnesium
intake and that can have quite some
consequences on your brain. In fact, if
we take a deeper look at how magnesium
affects our brain, we get a great idea
of why deficiencies can be so
detrimental. That's partly shown here.
In this study, which is a mechanism
study, researchers wanted to know if you
supplement with magnesium, does it enter
the brain? among many other things. As
we can see here, mice that were fed a
magnesium experienced an increase in
brain magnesium. To be clear, this is
also true for humans. We can see that
when comparing the zero time there to
the 24 days, one of the magnesium
conditions experiences an increase in
the fluid surrounding the brain called
the cerebral spinal fluid. Now, what
does it do once it's there? Well, in
cognitive tests between magnesiumfed and
non-magnesium, so controlfed mice, we
see as indicated by the lines going up
that magnesium improved cognitive
performance. Essentially, they're taking
the result from the control group and
subtracting that from the magnesium
group and any rise in the line indicates
a difference or benefit of the magnesium
group. Okay, so we know that it goes
into the brain and we know that it
improves cognitive ability, but we
should go a layer deeper because what
exactly is this ion magnesium doing to
our brain? You might already know this,
but your brain has a variety of cells
that make up its structure. And even
within those cells, there are
differences, but we'll focus on a major
type of cell. The cell that allows you
to think, to zone out to this video, to
write comments telling me to get to the
point, and allows you to do many things
is called the neuron. In a general
explanation, your neurons communicate
using two opposite ends of themselves.
So, one is called the dendrite, the
other is called the axon. The dendrite
is where the input from other neurons is
accepted, and the axon is where the
output to other neurons is relayed. So
the more of these connections there are
between cells, the stronger the
signaling between cells. Again,
generally because there are some
exceptions. So the more of these axons,
for example, that are in an area of the
brain, the greater the chance to relay
electrical and chemical signals from one
neuron to the next, which is where we
get to those wonderful abilities that I
was talking about. You know, like
clicking to join the physionic insiders.
Too soon. Sorry. The point being the
more connections between these vital
brain cells and neurons the better the
brain would function. So magnesium plays
a role as we see here. The researchers
have used an immunofllororescent stain
to tag a particular protein called
synaptofizzen which is in this context a
marker of axon terminals the end of the
axon that we discussed. So the more
synaptofizzen the more axon terminals
are in an area greater density. So good
thing I think that the uh images
themselves control on the left and the
magnesium on the right indicate already
that there's more green in the right
image the magnesium treated image but if
we look at the average results across
multiple experiments we see that
confirmed. So as the black the magnesium
group bar is elevated over the control.
They did some other experiments to
confirm these results as well. So this
study that we went over tells us that
greater brain magnesium levels improve
the connectivity or at least the density
between the neurons which is pretty
amazing. Okay, we at least know in
animal models that magnesium plays an
important role in our brain. But there
are a lot of outstanding questions. One,
does this apply to humans? Two, how do
we use this information? And three, what
bad news is still coming barreling down
Nick's neuronless brain? Let's address
the human aspect first. There is a study
that looked at human brain size. So, one
reason for the title of this video and
the link with dietary magnesium across
6,000 people. In that study, the
researchers identified that per 1
millgram increase in magnesium intake,
there was a link to a 0.001% 0001%
increase in gray matter, white matter
and size of a particular region of the
brain called the hippocampus. There were
also fewer lesions in the brain, areas
of loss of axons, so more inflammation
and general deterioration of the brain.
So overall an association with greater
brain size and better quality of brain
matter. We'll be coming back to this
study because I have something else to
say about it. The study that we just
went over is informative, but it doesn't
speak to the functional outcomes. As in,
sure, the brain is bigger, the brain has
better structure, but does that actually
prevent us from brain related disorders
like dementia? So, for that, there's a
recent analysis that included 15 studies
assessing the relationship between
magnesium intake and blood levels and
cognitive impairment. If we look here,
we're looking at a forest plot with
three of the 15 studies on the left side
there. Why not all 15? Because these
three were the only ones to assess
dietary intake of magnesium and dementia
specifically. The middle lines indicate
a neutral relationship. But if the big
diamond there moves to the right, that
indicates increased risk of dementia
from consuming above the estimated
average requirement or the e.
I'll go ahead and spoil it for you.
There's no relationship here. meaning
consuming more magnesium was not
associated with reduced dementia risk
compared to consuming less. But this has
some pretty glaring issues. If you'll
allow me to point them out because
there's some conflicting data within the
same analysis that we have to reconcile
this with the forest plot that we just
uh went over only includes three
studies. That alone can be a major
strike. However, they also segmented
based on a pretty crude black and white
cutoff above and below the estimated
average requirement. That is an
imprecise way of teasing out data,
although it may have been the only way
to do it. The below group was consuming
around 230 mg and the above group was
consuming 370 mg. That may not be enough
of a difference to tease out such a
drawnout condition like dementia.
Overall, the point is I don't think that
this is great quality data to make any
definitive claims. On the other hand,
the researchers analyzed the same data
but looked for a relationship per 100
mgram increase in magnesium intake. And
when assessing that data linearly, as in
300 milligs is better than 200
milligrams, which is better than 100
milligrams. They found no relationship
between magnesium and dementia. On the
other hand, when assessing nonlinearly,
they did find a relationship. So they
identified a U-shaped relationship, as
in consuming low levels of magnesium is
related to dementia, but consuming high
levels of magnesium was also related to
dementia.
Ah, now you're be beginning to see why
there might be some warnings associated
with all this. Another type of study
that we might be able to lean on because
we've been focused primarily on
correlation data except for the
mechanism study that we discussed is
randomized control trials. These heavily
indicate cause and effect. And there
have been three randomized control
trials on the topic looking at cognitive
measures. I won't bore you with the more
data, but I'll mention what happened
briefly. Two studies found an effect of
supplementing magnesium and the third
did not. Two of the studies were
classified as high risk of bias and all
three studies were small as well as in
people with serious health cons
complications
like cancer, liver cerosis uh in s
surgical patients. Woo. Okay, pick it
up, Nick. I should probably also mention
that in the meta analysis that we just
went over, the majority of the studies
were correlational. So I mentioned that
already, but because that's the case,
the researchers have to account for
potential explanatory factors.
Essentially, you have to scrub the data
for anything that might be the real
reason for this dementia risk was
increased or reduced. So for example,
did body weight also track with the same
as magnesium? then we can't tell if it's
the magnesium or the body weight that
led to the relationship with dementia
unless we remove body weight
relationship and see if the magnesium
relationship remains. So the researchers
did that accounting for all these
factors. However, one of the major
issues related to looking at a single
molecule like magnesium is the fact that
it isn't a big player like exercise,
body weight or overall en energy intake
and you know things of that nature. So,
how can we reasonably account for things
like calcium, sodium, and other related
nutrients? It's possible, but it takes
more robust adjustments than what we've
been over here. Not to mention, not all
included studies did the same
adjustments, even if there was
significant overlap.
Okay, let me give you one more piece of
bad news before I brighten your day with
today's sponsor. Miracle magnesium
mulberry marshmallows
packed with magnesium that may or may
not track with dementia. Packed with
sugar that really kickstarts your day
and a mere 500 calories per marshmallow.
This health snack will have you ripe for
obesity in no time. Oh, and they had
only limited input on my extremely
positive conclusions related to
magnesium at the end of this video. I
pinky promise. Just don't look at my
bank account. I promise you. I promise
you someone will take that seriously. It
happens every single time. No. But one
more piece of bad news and then I'll
shine a ray of hope and hopefully pack
this all up nicely for you to understand
and uh for some takeaways. So half of
you just let out an audible
finally.
Hey, I heard that I mentioned uh we'd
returned to this study and the reason is
that uh while they did find a
relationship between magnesium and brain
size, the sample size or the number of
participants that they based some of
their associations on was uh 1 to 3% of
the total sample. So the 6,000
participants total that especially
considering the effect size if you
calculate it out is about 0.1%
increase in brain size per 100 mg of
magnesium at least according to some
measures. So is that actually
meaningful? I honestly don't know. It
might be. But there's still a
relationship with magnesium and brain
size as well as brain quality. I just
wouldn't want to buy into particular
parts of this analysis with too much
gusto. To be fair, the 0.1% increase is
based on the total sample. So, all that
to say, there's a lot of problems in the
literature. But even so, we'll be able
to get an idea of how to think about
magnesium and our brain, assuming that
we're not deficient. Get it?
Before we do, my magnesium deficient
brain feels compelled to mention that if
you found that first study on how
magnesium affects our brain fascinating,
I have a deep dive on some other
incredible discoveries from that study,
some additional mechanisms, and some
more precise ways of linking magnesium
like blood levels to our brain through
other studies. If you're interested in a
deeper dive and if your brain isn't
scrambled from the science talk up to
now, check out the extended version of
this video that you're watching along
with the accompanying article in the
Physionic Insiders, my premium research
platform. You also get access to discuss
it with me and upcoming live sessions uh
also included with the membership. Oh,
and there's a podcast, a whole library
of other videos, articles, and much
more. You can join using the uh link in
the description. I might even be able to
snag you some M4s for you. That's the
miracle magnesium mulberry marshmallows.
Did you already forget? Come on. Okay,
so overall, magnesium is an important
nutrient. None of this literature that
we went over is saying otherwise.
Magnesium is also important for the
brain, and it's even strongly regulated
in the brain. And yes, being low in
magnesium intake does seem to track with
smaller brain volume. while consuming
more tracks with more brain volume as
well as better brain composition.
However, I did not think that the
evidence is good enough to create a
clear relationship between an exact
amount of magnesium intake and brain
health. In fact, I don't think that we
have evidence that more is necessarily
better. And even the researchers
themselves point out that we need more
studies, long-term associative studies
as well as adequate randomized control
trials. But there does seem to be enough
evidence that being too low repeatedly
shows poor associations with brain
health. So consuming below 240 milligs
of magnesium per day is too low. Then
going up from there, the data becomes a
lot murkier and impossible to tease out
the optimal. though I would stick to at
least the estimated average requirement
of 350 milligs per day for men and
around 260 millig for women. However,
that may also be very likely too low,
especially for other health metrics. So,
the recommended daily allowance of
around 400 mg for men and 320 milligs
for women seems a safer bet until we can
get better evidence at least for the
brain. But brain atrophy or brain
shrinking can also occur with age. And
there are specific foods that slow the
process impressively. You can check that
out right here. Thanks for tuning in.
See you.